Knolls Action Project; Records apap105
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Military Resistance and Nuclear Disarmament, 1965-1993; 7; 5.0 cubic ft.
  - Religious Groups and Issues, 1979; 1981-1985 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 22)
    See oversize box for copy of Economic Justice for All: Catholic social teaching and the U.S. economy (a documentary service of The Evangelist, Jan.1, 1987).
  - Reagan, 1982; 1984-1986 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 23)
    Clippings, articles, leaflets.
  - Karen Rembert's Statement, 1982-1983 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 24)
    Contains clippings, and Karen Rembert's explanation for leaving employment at Knolls.
  - Responsible Investments, 1983; 1985; 1988 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 25)
    Information on socially responsible financial investments.
  - The Ribbon, 1985-1986 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 26)
    Information regarding this national peace action.
  - SDI - Star Wars, 1984-1987 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 27)
    Clippings; articles, flyers from various organizations.
  - SUNY Peace Project, 1988 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 28)
  - Social Costs, 1981; 1983; 1985-1986; 1989 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 29)
  - Social Justice Center Business, 1991 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 30)
  - Social Workers, [Undated] (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 31)
    Includes a proposal to implement an educational outreach program for human service agency staff.
  - Solidarity Peace Fund (Pantex), 1982 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 32)
    Information regarding a fund used for employees of Pantex Plant who leave employment to seek work in non-military industry.
    See oversize box for copy of National Catholic Reporter.
  - Song Sheets - by John R., [Undated] (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 33)
  - Soviet Military Spending, 1981; 1987 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 34)
  - Soviet Threat/U.S. - Soviet Relations, 1980-1989 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 35)
  - Street Theater Ideas, [Undated] (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 36)
  - Technical Information-n-Arms; NARMIC Maps, 1979 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 37)
    Includes "How to build your own atomic bomb" (reprinted from Take Over). See oversize box for publication The Progressive (Nov. 1979).
  - Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons - 3rd Review Conference, 1985 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 38)
  - Two Guys, 1987-1988 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 39)
    Includes clippings and correspondence between GE and the GE Stockholders' Alliance Against Nuclear Power.
  - U.N. Special Session on Disarmament (SSDIII), 1988 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 40)
    Information pertaining to actions in support of the third U.N. Special Session on Disarmament.
  - U.N. Non-Governmental Liaison Service (N.G.L.S), 1976; 1985; 1986 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 41)
  - "Testament" - Story, 1980 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 42)
    Short story "Last Testament" by Carol Amen that inspired the movie Testament.
  - Taxes, 1983; 1985-1988 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 43)
    Leaflets and handouts regarding taxes and the military.
  - Watervliet Arsenal, 1982-1983; 1985; 1988 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 44)
    Includes a statement by congressman Samuel Stratton regarding local defense spending.
  - Women, 1982; 1984-1985; 1987 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 45)
    Includes leaflets, articles, handouts. See oversize box for poster "We are angry women", and publication WIN (1983).
  - Vietnam Veterans United to Prevent World War III, 1987 (Box 5 (7-Military Resistance and Nuclear ), Folder 46)
    Newsletters prepared by HEAL, American Friends Service Committee, Coalition for a New Foreign and Military Policy, Faith and Resistance Center for Nonviolent Studies, Syracuse Peace Council, Citizen Alert, the Nuclear Resister, Ground Zero Center for Nonviolent Action, Nuclear Weapons Freeze. Also, copies of The Niskayuna Journal, Current: The Journal of North Country Action, and the Progressive.
- Legal Documents, 1983-1990; 8; 1.0 cubic ft.
  This series contains the records of the ACLU case brought by KAP against KAPL challenging the leafleting restriction. There are copies of legal documents and transcripts from the trial and subsequent appeal. The series also includes transcripts from the trespass case (1988) and gag order case (1988).
  - ACLU Case: Appeal, 1985 (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 1)
  - ACLU Case: Complaint, 1983 March (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 2)
  - ACLU Case: Deposition of Maureen Casey, 1983 December (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 3)
  - ACLU Case: Examination of Theodore James, 1983 October (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 4)
  - ACLU Case: Examination of Alfred E. Kakretz, 1983 October (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 5)
  - ACLU Case: Examination of Daniel Kelly, 1983 October (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 6)
  - ACLU Case: Depositions of Louise McNeilly, 1983 December (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 7)
  - ACLU Case: Examination of Lance Stewart, 1983 October (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 8)
  - ACLU Case: Examination of Robert Traxler, 1983 October (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 9)
  - ACLU Case: Interrogatories, 1983 (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 10)
  - ACLU Case: KAPL Security Police Report, 1982 November (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 11)
  - ACLU Case: Memorandum of Law in Support of Defendants' Motion for Summary Judgment, 1984 January (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 12)
  - ACLU Case: Miscellaneous, 1983-1984 (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 13)
    Correspondence, notes, documents.
  - ACLU Case: Plaintiffs' Memorandum of Law in Opposition to Defendants' Summary Judgment Motion, 1984 January (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 14)
  - ACLU Case: Pre-Trial Stipulation, 1984 (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 15)
  - ACLU Case: Statement of Facts in Dispute, 1984 January (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 16)
  - ACLU Case: Statement of Facts Not in Dispute, 1984 January (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 17)
  - ACLU Case: Transcript, 1984 September (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 18)
  - ACLU Case: Trial, 1984 (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 19)
  - Clippings and Press Releases, 1982-1985 (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 20)
  - KAPL: Gag Order, 1988-1990 (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 21)
  - Leafleting Restriction, Spring/Summer 1982, 1982-1988 (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 22)
  - Trespass Case: Transcript (Niskayuna), 1988 (Box 1 (8-Legal Documents), Folder 23)
- Audiovisuals and Memorabilia, 1985; 1987; 1990-1991; ca. 1980s; 9; 35 cubic ft.
  The series contains a small collection of audio-visual materials. There is a slide show, cassette and script prepared by the National War Tax Resistance Coordinating Committee. There are several audio-tapes, including a 1990 radio interview with Jack Shannon, a former employee and "whistleblower" at KAPL, and a tape of the Seminar on Economic Conversion (January 10, 1987).
  There are also several oversize boxes of ephemera created for or used at demonstrations. Items in Box 2 include buttons with the slogan "I'd Rather Be Making Toys". These buttons were purchased by supporters for $1 and handed out to workers at the Knolls Atomic Power Laboratory. There are a few of the origami cranes that were given out to the Knolls workers on August 6, 1987, in commemoration of the atomic bomb being dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki. Balloons with anti-nuclear and anti-bomb slogans such as "I Want to Grow Up Not Blow Up" and "Blow Up Balloons Not People". There are also plastic cups and flowers, stickers, an inflatable fighter jet, and a raffle box created for one of the group's events. Box 3, Textiles, contains banners and fabric worn or used at demonstrations. The banners read: "Resist Nuclear War Preparations at Knolls Work For Peace", "Stop the Sub Not In Our Name", "Pentagon Tentacle Trident", and "No More Hibakusha".
  - 1. Slide show - "More than a Paycheck: War tax resistance in America" - Slide show, cassette and script prepared by the National War Tax Resistance Coordinating Committee, Undated (Box 1 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 1)
  - Deadly Deception: General Electric, Nuclear Weapons & Our Environment (30 second spot, INFACT), 1991 (Box 1 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Video-tape 1)
  - INFACT:Deadly Deception - 60-second spot, 1991 (Box 1 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Cassette 1)
  - INFACT:Deadly Deception (Mono 15 IPS), 1991 (Box 1 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Reel 1)
  - National War Tax Resistance Coordinating Committee, Undated (Box 1 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Cassette 2)
  - Whistleblowers - WGY radio interview with Jack Shannon, 1990 (Box 1 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Cassette 3)
  - Seminar on Economic Conversion, Undated (Box 1 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Cassette 4)
    Guest speaker Karen Clark, Minnesota state legislator and chair of the committee on economic conversion for Minnesota. There are recordings on both sides of the tape
  - Inflatable toy fighter jet, Undated (Box 2 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 1)
  - Plastic flowers, Undated (Box 2 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 2)
  - Buttons - "I'd Rather Be Making Toys", purchased by KAP supporters and given to KAPL workers, ca. 1980s (Box 2 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 3)
  - Stickers, Undated (Box 2 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 4)
  - Balloons, Slogans: "Blow Up Balloons Not People", and "I Want To Grow Up Not Blow Up", Undated (Box 2 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 5)
  - Origami Cranes, Handed out to KAPL workers with the leaflet of August 6, 1987 in commemoration of the atomic bomb dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki, 1987 August 6 (Box 2 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 6)
  - Plastic Cups, Undated (Box 2 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 7)
  - Raffle Box, Undated (Box 2 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 8)
  - Banner, "Resist Nuclear War Preparation At Knolls Work For Peace", ca. 1980s (Box 3 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 1)
  - Banner, "Stop the Sub Not in Our Name", possibly used at demonstrations in opposition to the nuclear submarine named after the city of Albany, ca. 1980s (Box 3 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 2)
  - Banner, "Pentagon Tentacle Trident", ca. 1980s (Box 3 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 3)
  - Banner, "No More Hibakusha", ca. 1980s (Box 3 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 4)
  - Fabric, Possibly used as headbands or for banners, ca. 1980s (Box 3 (9-Audiovisuals and Memorabilia), Item 5)
- Oversize Material, Undated; 10
  Material in series that required oversize storage containers:
  Oversize 1: Series 1 through Series 6.
  Oversize 2: Series 7 Box 1 through Series 7 Box 3.
  Oversize 3: Series 7 Box 4 through Series 7 Box 5.
  Oversize 4: Series 9 Box 2.
  Oversize 5: Series 9 Box 3.